I don't know how much Sean has told you.
Not very much.
He was surprised in some cases, but interested in my background.
And said, well, I know somebody who would like to talk to you.
And then you mentioned in your email what your function is, so.
Yeah.
I'm just, I'd like to do background on people I'm interviewing.
So I did a little digging.
And just to see that you worked here in the 90s, is that right?
Did you work here in the 90s?
Is that what the time was?
Yeah, I came in 1985 and retired the first one in 2000.
Then they called me back.
You know, it's like bad cars, they get recalled.
And so I retired again in 2002 and again in 2003.
You can't stay away.
Well, my replacement kept either quitting or not coming.
And at that time, in fact, that's what I came for, is they had the beginning of a separate telecommunication program, separate from electronic, the common base for, I guess,
Yeah, freshman and sophomore, and then they branch out into telecom.
And my role was to develop the telecom part.
Yeah, so when they did call me back, I said, well, I'm retired.
They said, yeah, but you've got juniors that can't graduate because there's nobody offered a course.
Yeah.
Okay, okay.
That's a tricky situation.
It's like they got you there.
They know which button to push.
I wasn't forced to accept.
Right.
So I'm going to be honest.
I know about technology.
I'm not very technologically savvy.
So I was doing a little background research too into your field.
It very quickly turned into another foreign language to me.
But it was so interesting seeing how you were part of the
great technological shift on the university, like you were part of that, you were there, you saw that.
Yeah, well, that period of time, telecom was booming, and the technology was also moving very fast.
But we actually got after the...
second, third year, a separate accreditation for the telecom program, ABET accreditation, so that was good.
Yeah, absolutely.
We were, I think, the second strictly telecom program as opposed to electronic, electricity.
and the first undergraduate to get accredited.
So that was good.
Yeah, absolutely.
Sorry that I'm jumping right into this, but how was that process of getting accredited?
What did that entail?
Oh, that's a very long process.
There's this much paperwork.
They want to know all the description of the program, how many people, students do you have, how many graduates, how many have
are employed, et cetera, et cetera.
But each course, again, a detail, not just a summary.
They want to see everything on the course.
It's a very long preparation process.
And everybody has to do it, but...
Does that go to like, whenever you finish that, does that go to like a national type of?
Yeah, yes.
And so you submit that and so professors of other universities that have a telecom program or something related or are professionally involved in telecom review all of these and then decided, yeah, let's go visit or not.
And so there's a group of three or four people that come and spend two, three days here looking at the labs, looking at the, talking, interviewing the students.
It's a good process, but it takes a lot of time.
Yeah, I can definitely see that.
I would love to get you in touch with this gentleman named Mark Baggett.
He does,
the technological services for the library, but he has access to the supercomputers that we have here.
So I was like, I feel like that's something... Well, that's a different orientation, but...
Can you tell me about where you were born and where you were raised?
I was born in Paris, France, just before World War II in 1937.
We had to, because of the German army invasion of France, we had to move, I think, three or four times during that period to, well, it's...
I was just a kid, I was a little kid, so, but I do remember, suddenly, no, we gotta go, and it was not like next month, it's tomorrow.
Who was in your family at that time?
Well, my kids, I was an only child, but my...
Let's see, yeah, my biological father had to leave because of the war situation and mother was left alone with me.
But later on, I guess, I don't know the details,
My parents divorced, and again, I know he had gone overseas.
And I don't know the details.
Mother didn't want to talk about it.
Right.
But she remarried.
And that, amazingly, that new father of mine, I mean, literally adopted me.
And we went through the war and...
And he took a chance because he was,
I don't remember which level, co-director of a factory.
And of course, Germans took that over and so we left again.
So it was, and all the bombardments and this and that.
Can I ask his name and your mom's name?
I don't know if they want that.
Yeah, I think I'll pass on that.
Sorry.
Well, actually, my biological father, you can have his first name was René.
He was a, he had a, from what I read much later on, he had a PhD in marine biology.
And in fact, went to, that was after the war was over, went to New Caledonia, which is a small island in the Pacific, north of New Zealand, way north, and set up an aquarium there.
He founded the aquarium and became quite famous in his field.
Wow.
It's three, we published three big books.
So, but I actually, no, he left, that was a year and a half, I think.
And I never met him.
Well, that's on the other side of the world, literally.
Right, yeah.
Well, we stayed in touch, writing letters and things.
But your mom, how strong, how strong, wow.
Yeah, she had to, she had to face lots of other problems.
Well, single mother and, you know, the financial input that disappeared, so she had to find a job.
And yeah, and she has her own Ph.D. in sociology.
Wow.
So I had two imposing parents.
Yeah, very educated.
How did you end up...
That was a long circuitous thing.
I studied in France for high school, of course, and then it's like a junior college, but it's specialized.
It was strictly radio and electronics, except for some civics type things.
And then I did my military service in France for three years in their equivalent of the Signal Corps.
So I was radio again.
Since I had done two years of radio school, that made sense for them to put me there.
And after that, I worked at Paris for a year and a half.
And then a friend of mine, who I met in France several times, said, I had mentioned it, he said, you know, you need to come and visit us.
I said, well, yeah, but financial, I think, plus.
He said, well, and then he actually got me a work permit for a year.
So I went there, and the idea was,
well I'll work and I'll save as much money as possible and then I'll play tourist and but the it's not the case anymore but we're talking 1964-65 the telecom technology in the US was easily 10 years ahead of the French one
the telephone network at that time.
You know, there was no internet and digital transmission at that time, but telephone network in France.
It was not a priority, and the telecom was government-owned, like most of Europe.
Yeah, almost, yeah, actually, all of Europe.
The postal service and the telecommunications were government-owned.
And the telephone network, I mean, this is not, it's what, 10 years after the end of World War II, they had a lot of other problems and their decision was, yeah, we have a telephone network, we'll modernize it later, we got to use the money.
for other things, yeah.
So that, I discovered that very quickly, that wow, this is fascinating.
And they, they,
I'm a ham radio operator, so I met some American ham.
I was in New Hampshire for that work.
And one of them, actually, well,
I told him that my work permit was going to expire.
And he said, well, you know, hold on.
He had a small repair and installation shop for mobile radios.
and he was specialized in equipping and maintaining radios for fire departments.
Most of them volunteer fire departments around the south of New Hampshire.
And he said, I had the technician who messed up seriously almost six months ago, and I desperately need somebody.
He said, would you be interested?
Yep.
Well, let's see what I can do.
And so I guess he convinced the immigration folks that I really need somebody and I haven't been able to find a small town in New Hampshire.
And so I got another work permit.
And while I was doing that, I met a young lady who is now my wife, and we've been married for 57 years, I think.
So made the right decision, obviously.
So I worked there, and then same thing, you know, I've got a one-year period.
So I went to immigration in Boston.
and said, is there any way I can renew this?
And I said, no, surely by now we would have been able to find somebody.
And we discussed, and I started the paperwork, and I still remember the lady went to talk to her boss, I guess, and came back and said,
There is one possible.
If you can find a teaching job, you can stay.
We'll give you whatever it's called.
It's not the green card, it's definitely a work permit and also a temporary status, I guess.
But you can't leave New Hampshire.
I said, okay, I can leave.
But that was kind of mid-July.
And I go, ooh, school starts in, what, four weeks?
And that was marvelous.
I was in a little town in Peterborough, New Hampshire, and four different families went all around looking for, you know, do you need me?
And they...
I had essentially given up.
I started making reservations to go back.
And I got one of my friends who was a retired Air Force officer colonel.
called me and said, I got somebody, but you gotta hop.
I said, okay.
Turns out it's a junior college and their math professor, a lady, turned really sick.
And she said,
And I said, well, we need somebody to teach you calculus one and two, right?
Okay, I haven't done that, but I did study that way back.
And so he was the president of the college, not president, director, yeah, must have been president of the college, wrote a letter and said, take that to immigration.
And the same lady said, well, okay, I'm impressed.
So now I had
And that was valid for two years, I think, yeah.
And so, and as I said, I had met my wife there, which, so I had now all kinds of reasons for, it'd be nice.
I asked her, it turned out she's from Germany.
which is interesting.
She's much younger than I am, so we were the start of the year old.
Yeah, when we decided, when we got serious with each other, we went to Europe to meet our respective in-laws.
My mother had lots of friends, a lot of friends.
She was working as a translator for German and English to French.
And I knew several of her friends were Jewish and had serious problems during the war.
And here I come with a German girl.
And I thought, well, wait, she's much younger than I am.
That was not true.
It certainly wasn't her fault, but even, you know, she was born toward, after the war was over.
So I had all kinds of reasons prepared, but I had forgotten how the French, especially the Parisians, think.
And they didn't say, but she's German.
They said, wait, she isn't French.
I wasn't prepared for that.
Yeah, well, I didn't go to the U.S. to specifically look for a French girl.
That was funny.
But we got along with our respective in-laws.
So after the two years in the junior college, I decided to go back to school.
So I got a student visa, University of New Hampshire, electrical engineering, and I got bachelor's and master's from there.
And in the process, somebody said, you know, you're legal with your student status, but you've been here for so long, why don't you try applying for a green card?
And so I did.
And it's when I was a senior at the university, I got a letter saying, okay, we've got the Green Cup, but you've got to register for the draft.
Oh, the middle of the Vietnam War, right?
So I went there, and I still remember the master sergeant who was interviewing me.
He said, yeah, okay, so what's your background, et cetera, et cetera.
He said, you know, I just did three years military.
He looked at me, he said,
Wrong army, buddy.
Yeah.
I admit.
So sign up here.
And then toward the end, because then I had to take a physical and this, and then I came back to him and he said, you forgot to write your birth date.
Yeah, sorry.
I said, wait, you're over 27, so you're right, we need you to register, but unless we declare officially a war, you're too old.
Okay, I guess that's a compliment.
So about, I don't know, several months later, I got the green card, and
Dang, you get to serve in one army and then almost.
Yeah, and I wasn't, I had to think about that.
Do I really want to go to Vietnam and fight over there?
Well, yeah, I think it's worth it.
Besides, my wife had no interest in going back to live in Germany.
So she's staying here.
I think I'm staying here, if possible.
What was, did your wife work?
Yeah, well, when I met her, she was working in a pharmacy, not as a pharmacist, but to help the customers and things.
And then when I decided to go to the university, she, for some reason, followed me.
And she worked in the pharmacy there, but she was working part-time and going to secretary school.
So she was also really busy.
She had a green card already.
She came as, you know what au pair means?
Yeah.
She was a major, I think.
for whom she had babysitted his kids while he was stationed in Germany and done other things.
And so they knew each other very well.
And he said, come on over.
And then she was au pair with him for, I don't know, three years, something like that.
A good amount of time.
Yeah, yeah.
So, university...
Yeah, bachelor's, master's.
And then I worked for what was then General Telephone, which is now Verizon in Massachusetts, just outside of Boston.
I was with them for five years.
and then did something I wanted to do for decades.
I wanted to go overseas and help the people.
I mean, I'm not a doctor, and I'm not, but if they need help with telecom, maybe I can do training and things like that.
And so I had applied to the UN as a specialized agency called the International Telecommunication Union.
And one branch of that is development for less developed countries.
So I applied, I had applied already coming out of the radio school and they said, well, we don't take people at the technician level.
So once I got bachelor's degree, I reapplied and they said, yeah, that's good.
But we prefer, since you're going in those countries, you really need another, I mean, a higher degree.
And it turned out they were absolutely right.
In most of these countries, people will not take...
I don't want to call it orders, but directives from somebody who is not at a higher level than they are.
And they were absolutely right.
So I got my master's and I applied again.
and it's very good we'd like to have you but since you're going to be the specialist over there they call it an expert which is unfortunate because then you go there and well you're expert in everything telecom so no i never worked at those guys they said you were there anyhow so uh you know you you have some experience in the military and some but
again, you need to have a lot of experience, otherwise they're not going to listen to you.
So five years, ooh.
So that's where I went to work for General Telephone.
So after, and while I was there, after the five years, I reapplied.
No, I actually didn't.
I got a letter from the ITU saying we got, we revised your, not revised, we reviewed your application and we noticed you got five years now.
We'd like to have you
there are three possible positions for you.
And one was Equatorial Guinea.
And you know, it's, as the name indicates, they're right on the equator, right in Africa.
And so we think temperature and humidity here is bad, but over there, and they don't have air conditioning.
People were telling me, no, we changed shirts at least twice a day, if not three times.
And I didn't want to go there alone, right?
So by then we had, the twins were born, so no.
Okay, what's the other?
Saudi Arabia with my wife and two daughters?
No, sorry.
Well, we have one in Jamaica.
Ah, that sounds good.
So I took that job.
That was for two years.
They asked me to stay for an extra year.
Then as I was ready to come back to the U.S., my
Boss's boss in Geneva, where the specialized agency is, actually came and said, we started something in Haiti.
We need somebody who speaks French.
Well, I think I qualify with that.
But Haiti, yeah.
He said, hey, how about take your wife and kids and come for, while you help us write the proposal, they can go around.
Well, and that was during Baby Doc, the dictator there.
But Jamaica had its own problem.
The two major political parties, and they were literally fighting each other, and it was, it was, they,
they left foreigners alone, which is good.
But there were a whole region of Kingston, the capital of Jamaica, where, you know, just don't go there.
So we get to Haiti, and it's
I mean, wait, what's going on?
It's so calm here.
Of course, found out later why he'd get out of, you know.
baby dog, full dictatorship, and so you don't mess around.
But I remember walking with him one evening, and we kind of lost our way, and we were in the harbor area, and I thought, oh, that's not a good idea.
And people came to ask us, not for money, or what the heck, are you doing it, but are you lost?
Can we help you?
That's different.
So based on that, many other things.
The job was very interesting.
So after discussion with my wife and then three daughters, we went there for three years, which ended up being six.
So I did a lot of training and organizations.
And then my next post was going to be, still with the UN, it was going to be in Brazil.
And I told him by then, he was my direct boss, now he was in Geneva.
because I was project manager.
And I said, I don't speak Portuguese.
I said, you're going to a research center.
They all speak English.
Good.
But wait a minute.
Can I have some details of, you know, research center?
Yeah, telecom research center.
They're pretty advanced.
They have PhDs.
What do you want me for?
I don't have a PhD.
We've got all kinds of people, researchers.
What we need is something to keep them together, and we need a team leader.
You've been the project manager there for three years.
Okay, if you say so.
So I talked to my wife and the kids.
They said, no.
By that time, the twins were 17.
We are going back to the U.S. You can go where you want.
Okay, get overruled.
So we came back to the U.S.
And well, it's time to look for a job.
And one of our
Specialized Magazine, the IEEE, the Institute of Electronic and Electrical Engineering.
They have many magazines.
And I looked at the job openings, the opening in Texas here, and I said, hmm, for telecoms specifically.
That's unusual.
That sounds good.
So we came and visited.
I got interviewed and I liked it.
So I had to convince all my girls.
And one argument I use is to say, look, this is a nine-month contract, so I've got three months of vacation.
Think of all the time we're going to spend together.
Forty years later, they still remind me.
So when I was spending all this time together...
I say, yeah, it's a nine-month contract, but you do have 12 months of work.
But I mean, I don't regret it at all.
Admittedly, if I had known ahead of time, I probably wouldn't have taken it.
But I'm glad I did.
Yeah, absolutely.
It's, I mean, that...
So, 19 years, 19 and a half years here teaching.
Wow.
We've been everywhere it seems.
The summers were, you know, taken, well, one thing, as I say, telecom, technology was...
increasing and improving very quickly so one part of my summer is to catch up with this because I should teach them and that takes a long time then the books are by definition at least a year behind usually two because it takes a year to write it and then
So I put my own notes based on what I had learned in conferences and in specialized magazines and get copyrights and things like that.
That takes a long time.
And then you have to find a way to get scholarship for these people.
You can't do that during the year because you...
and then also equipment for the lab.
So the summers were pretty busy.
Ellie, my wife, would often say, no, wait a minute, industry, you had at least two weeks guaranteed, right?
Three, but here you can't?
No, I've got to do that.
I figured with all the summer months where I was either not paid at all or half salary,
I essentially worked nine and a half months for free.
Not consecutively, but over the...
Which, again, I don't regret.
When I left, we had three labs, telecom labs.
with equipment, a couple million dollars worth of equipment.
When I came, there was half a lab, and then two courses.
I left, there were nine courses, because each year I would add an additional lab.
That also takes time, by the way.
But I had several offers from industry as I went along,
So, obviously I stayed, and I guess I thoroughly enjoy the relationship with the students, and I felt, you know, former students, some of them still email me, or we meet somewhere, and they're grateful, and we thank you so much.
I thought you hated my test.
I did, but they were very useful.
Yeah.
There's something to be said about that.
I really don't regret it at all.
So that's good.
So the process of, because you said you came and there wasn't like a full program, so you helped build the program.
Yeah, yeah.
That was my role.
That was my, I guess, it was official title in the department.
I don't know if it was true in the college, but I was telecommunication course leader.
because I was developing all those, which is fine.
And I started as an assistant prof, but of course then you got to do a lot of research and publishing.
And I was reminded of that by the...
by the department head, right?
Several of them over the years.
And they said, we love you here, and you're doing a good job, but you've got to do research.
I said, that's not what I came for.
I came for teaching.
Research, I can get a lot better funding in industry.
And they said, yeah, but I can't keep you as assistant prof.
I said, well, any alternative?
And I reminded them, you know, this is an accredited program, right?
And I think I had something to do.
He said, absolutely, but the rule is, which is true.
And he said, well, you can be a lecturer.
I was a lecturer in grad school.
How about senior lecturer?
Let me check.
Then he came back from the dean and said, yeah, okay, you're on.
All right.
But you realize you can never get tenure.
I didn't come for that.
If I'm in the ministry, they can kick me off in two weeks, right?
Here, I've got that list at the end of the semester, so always.
I didn't realize that you would still have to do research.
Oh, yeah.
If you want tenure, there's no research and publishing.
You've got to publish books, or at least articles, and preferably books.
And I had started writing a book on testing telecommunication equipment because, well, I've used those, I've seen those, but...
So the students need it when they get there.
But that takes a lot of time.
And after the second chapter, I had already contacted the editor who was interested.
I said, you know, I know I told you I would do that, but it's either I continue with that at the expense of the students.
You can't do that.
So, that was another reason why it stayed.
Okay, from a perspective,
from a, what's the right word?
Sure, if you have an assistant associate prof, that sounds much better than senior lecturer, but who cares?
This is not what I came here for.
So you really enjoy the teaching aspect of it.
Oh yeah, totally.
Yes, very much so.
And again, you know, I had a close, of course, the telecom...
Typically, I had in each course something like between 20 and 25 students, so you can know them, you can relate both ways.
In fact, I told the seniors the first time, I said, okay, now that you're seniors, you can call me Pierre.
And they loved that.
One of my...
Yeah, I think his title was coordinator.
It's an assistant department head type thing.
who somehow one of the students mentioned that, you know, they call it, and he was a retired Air Force guy, recently retired, and he said, that's not acceptable.
And he told the students, don't ever do that again, because students came and said, oh, yeah.
I said, let me go talk.
And he gave me a hard time.
I said, you're going to lose respect.
The only reason they respect me is if I'm called by my last name, then I, you know.
I said, no, but it's just not done, which is true.
And then the department had overheard the discussion.
He said to him, he said, you're not in
So that continued, and the seniors loved it.
That was their graduation to senior level.
And I, yeah, I,
When I started, I started with, there was an introductory course to telecom for the sophomores, and then a poorly defined telephone request.
network, let's say.
But as I said, that expanded a lot.
I had an industrial advisory board like most programs do, but we were president or equivalent of telephone companies all over Texas and others.
You know, Southwestern Bell, NGT, and...
When I came at first, the first semester, it's a long, I don't know if I'm diverging too much, but these people involved with telephone companies had asked, I guess, the then College of Engineering
I'm trying to remember, well, it won't be an exact thing, but they said, look, we need some telecom people, you know, sure, you're sending us electronic, you know, electrical, electronic people, but then we have to train them for six months, because that's, you don't teach this stuff.
And the then dean of the College of Engineering, this is 1985, right?
Well, no, in fact, it was before I came, so now...
and said, oh, but what you want us to do, that's not university level.
That's a technician program.
No, no, we want engineers, but we want a specialized engineer.
Sorry, we can't do that.
We don't do that here.
And so, I don't remember the details since I wasn't there, I'm just trying to recollect, but somebody in the college said to them, said, wait, why don't you try the engineering technology department?
They are not training people for grad school, they're training people for industry.
So they went, and so in engineering and technology, they said, yeah, well, we can do that.
So they started that one and a half course I'm talking about.
And so when I came, those same people, presidents of different sales companies came, and we had a meeting, and that's,
I introduced myself and said, there are several ways I can orient that.
I did graduate from electronic programs.
Are you interested in them designing circuits or are you interested in them applying the existing equipment in the best possible?
I said, circuits we have from electrical engineers.
We got plenty of those.
That's not what we want.
We don't want to have spent six months training everybody.
Oh, good, that's where I came from, system side.
And they were, so that I developed the different courses based on my experience, but also saying, okay, but what do you people want more specifically?
What kind of technology are you using?
And so we started things to respond to that.
Because they were pleased with the department and with the graduates, they started offering some equipment.
And I remember that was after several years.
But I kept a relationship with those guys, and we were fairly close.
And I asked one of them, I said, I won't mention the company, but I said, you know, I'm impressed by the amount of equipment you're giving us and the scholarships.
He said, well, there's something special about your program.
We noticed your equipment within a semester or so has been set up and is working.
We know you're doing something with it.
There are other places where that thing just sits there for whatever reason, for years.
I said, well, I can keep doing that.
Keep doing that.
So, and yeah, I mean, and the scholarships, too.
That was...
And because, well, okay, I get some credit there, because the program was good and correctly oriented.
And because telecom was booming at that time, all my students, if they had C or better, had a job before they graduated.
Some of them went on the internship, but even besides that, they came here and they would tell, which didn't please the recruiting folks over there.
They said, no, no, no, we want to talk to the engineering technology telecom group.
But we have many.
Yes, we know.
Everybody got a job.
You had to have a seat.
That's fair enough, right?
That's impressive.
One of the petroleum company, they had their own, like all of a large corporation, they have their own telecom network, privately owned.
So they have a telecom group that takes care of that.
And their director of that group...
Now you ask them, I would go and visit them, that particular thing was in Chicago.
And I asked him over dinner, he said, you know, I'm really grateful that you are hiring my C students.
And they said, well, but I've told our recruiting folks, if they come from your program, add a letter to that, go up.
So your Cs are my Bs, and that's fine.
That's high praise.
I like that, yeah.
Yeah, it was great.
Well, you know, there's a big satellite antenna next to Tom, so that was given to us.
And we used that until I left, I guess.
I hesitate to open the door and see what's inside, because I know it hasn't been used since.
But, yeah, I mean, it was great.
It was great.
How did you keep up with, since the technology was changing so quickly, how did you keep up with that?
Yeah, well, that was strenuous, I would say.
One thing is conferences.
I would go in the summer and sometimes during the year as well.
Big telecoms, some of them at the national level,
conferences and people present their new stuff and you meet people that can help you.
If you have any questions, just give me a call, do it.
A lot of that I didn't know.
You have to learn.
So that was one big thing.
The other thing is I had the possibility that I could go there and just
spend the day in the company looking around talking to their engineers and things like that that helps a lot and they would say you know there there is this thing again that was not internet yet we had just email but
And specialized magazines.
But yeah, it takes a lot of time.
And some of the staff say, wait a minute, I better go ask somebody here.
How does that work?
But I was thoroughly interested in that, so that you're willing to go deeper and longer than you would otherwise.
I remember talking with one of my colleagues from the English department, and I said, you guys are lucky.
Things don't change, right?
And so you've got three months off in the summer.
He said, yeah.
You know how boring it is to teach Shakespeare's to freshmen again and again, and they couldn't care less.
Which is a good point, because by, since, except the first four years, all the courses I was teaching were at the junior and senior level.
And if they've reached that point, obviously they're interested.
And that makes it, we had some very interesting discussion.
I used, not every year, but for quite a while.
I had, once a week, I had an evening thing.
You guys come and ask questions.
We just, you know, and we'd bring pizza and just discuss whatever they're interested in.
And they...
So I was never bored.
Never bored.
You seem like the type of professor that students would seek out, that they would actually go to, feel comfortable with.
Well, and open office doors.
If I'm there, the door is open.
Unless there's a student that comes in and has some problem.
He or she doesn't want other people to hear.
But that helped, too.
There were many national-level conferences, but one in particular...
was specifically for the telecom, I think, for the large companies that had their own private telecom.
So there's a whole group of people that you don't, well, the general public
doesn't think of.
That's a telephone company or the internet company.
But they have very elaborate networks and they usually move with the technology faster than the telephone companies do because of budget and other reasons.
So
So I almost always went to these groups.
And after a while, in fact, when we became accredited, I got invited and said, you can bring four of your students.
And so I would pick my four top students.
And I told them ahead of time, you know,
I'm not going to, this is not a condition, but if I take just my four students and they can come with me on this, so they have to pay for the airplane thing, but the conference is free, the room is free, the food is free.
And you're going to be...
in an environment where you have the most recent equipment.
That helped too.
And of course, I would meet these other telecom managers and, oh, we didn't know you had the telecom program.
Yeah, it was good.
That's good.
When the department offered me a nice retirement reception in the former student,
And so, you know, the speech and thing, and in mind, I used the occasion to publicly apologize to my daughters and wife for never being there.
Never, but that's true.
Yeah, that was, I retired two more times, and then they said, well, we're not offering you, no, that was so good, that's so well done, that was worth three.
This seems silly that I haven't asked this yet, but how did you first get interested in telecom?
Ham radio, yeah, that was definitely...
Yes, that was the start.
I started going to meetings, ham radio meetings, and then met others, and then got my...
In France, you had to build your own transmitter too.
But, so, that was, and I had a mentor, if you want to have, and then, that's why I went to that radio school after high school, rather than wherever.
Interesting.
Something, I'm not saying it's simple, but something as simple as a hand radio got you
all the way from your country, all the way over here, and all these opportunities.
It's so interesting.
Well, and that first work permit, Wesleyan Radio Guy, and it changed my life, really, for something very good.
And you come to a brand new place, right?
And you know nobody.
Just pick up your radio and talk through the repeaters.
Oh, you know, come to our meetings.
And so suddenly you've got four or five, six people that are there talking.
common interest and they know this and that.
So, yeah, that helped me considerably.
That's awesome.
That's interesting.
And it's even in the military service that I was, well,
I first went to NCO school and became a sergeant, but that was in the Signal Corps, so in radio.
And then I was based not far from Paris because I graduated
I was the second or third in line when I graduated from NCO school.
So you had choices, right?
The first guy, okay, what's your preference for the first year?
After that, we'll send you when we need you.
And I was like third, something like that.
definitely among the first ten.
And the guy said, well, sorry, all the places in Germany, because at that time, you know, there was the British, the Americans, the French, the, but no more space there.
And there's also, oh, there's a place outside of Paris that
That's our telecom training center.
That sounds good.
And I didn't tell him that, especially my parents live just across.
So you're half an hour on bicycle.
Oh yeah.
I was lucky there.
And in fact,
In that time, military service was mandatory in France, so you had to go.
But they would take you wherever they needed so that you could find yourself, regardless of your background, you know, as a truck driver or whatever.
But one of the hams in a monthly meeting was a...
At that time, he was either major or lieutenant colonel, but he was, we saw him often.
He came, I guess he was stationed not far from Paris either.
And he told me and a friend who was also in the radio school, said, you know,
If you want to be in the single corps, the only way that you can be sure of that is to enlist rather than wait to be constricted.
So mandatory with 18 months, a year and a half.
If you're enlisted, it's minimum three years.
So he said, your choice, but I would recommend you do it that way, and you also, through your first year,
You become a sergeant, which has some advantages.
And so I talked it over with my friend and said, yep, let's go that way.
And I remember my dad saying, a doctor, that's it.
you're gonna win this uh yeah but oh okay so and and this so that was a him too and in fact i
The third year, the last year of the service, I was in that train center doing training for people to maintain and repair high-power transmitters and things like that.
And we have a new commanding officer coming in.
And so, you know, we will wait for him in decent speech.
I look at him, he's in full uniform, of course.
I thought, I know this guy.
I couldn't figure out why.
And that was the guy.
And so he called me in his office later and said,
We know each other, and we're both hams, but you do remember that I'm, so, and it's not a personal thing, but you know, other officers are there, so please remember that I'm Colonel, so I'm, yes sir.
But as a reward, there is a ham radio station on the floor above my office, which has been inactive.
So you need to get that thing back on the air and use it to call and let people know that this is... That sounds like a good deal, sir.
Yeah, I mean, all my life, ham radio is played...
Um, the decision to enlist, that must have been scary, especially considering the time period.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, there's a, especially now, I mean, I'm 88, so, but, it's still in New Hampshire.
I remember a reunion on D-Day, June 4th, sorry, June 6th, 1944.
And there were several retired officers there, including the one that got me the teaching job.
And I said, well, where were you on your barbecue and things?
I said, where were you on D-Day?
I'm in the U.S. somewhere, in the Pacific, and I said,
And it comes to me, and I'm like, you know, at least 10 years younger, if not 15, than they are.
I said, well, I guess I was the only one in Normandy.
And the lawyer said, you enlisted age eight?
You didn't ask.
I wasn't on the beach, but you asked.
where were you in the field?
I was in Normandy.
I happened to be a seven-year-old kid when you guys came along and I was glad to see you.
But that was...
Yeah, I mean, during the war, there were some very close calls.
In fact, we moved from Paris to the south of France because, I don't know if you know that, but the armistice with the Germans said, okay, we're occupying the northern part of France and the rest is
I mean, they're both France, but that's under French authority, and this is, of course, that didn't last very long.
So we moved from Paris to the south of France.
And then when the Nazis occupied the south part, we moved out and went.
And I kidded my dad for a long time that we went to Normandy, not on the beach, right, on the small village.
And I kidded him afterwards and said, of all the places, and he said,
Everybody knew that the Allied weren't silly enough to try to scale the Atlantic Wall with all the protection and all the forts and all that.
They're going to come from England.
Well, they came from England, but directly or from the Mediterranean.
And he's right.
At that time, including Hitler, unfortunately, he thought...
So it was quiet until about a year before 1944, because then it started.
We were in a small village.
There was a train line going through the village, and of course...
trained with ammunitions and, you know, you name it, going back and forth.
So that was dangerous by itself.
But the British Air Force and the American would bomb these things, you know, because we don't want that to get... Yeah, but...
So there were two...
two big hills in that village.
And they had caves to make Galvados the equivalent of Cognac, if you want.
So pretty deep.
So whenever there was an alert or you heard the bombers coming to half of the village go there, and sometimes they, certainly overnight and sometimes days and days.
And some of the bumps came pretty close.
I mean, we lucked out.
It's, yeah.
And then, you know, the German occupation of the village, and so, you know, they get all the food and, I mean, all the meat and all the good stuff, and we eat turnips and rutabagas for weeks.
And you never knew what would happen.
And, you know,
Yeah, I mean, those two years were painful, to say the least.
And we lucked out.
It could have been much worse.
I'm glad it turned out for the better.
Yeah.
And the village, fortunately, didn't have any strategic value.
Our village didn't get liberated by the Americans until August something, early August.
So, you know, the D-Day was June 6, right?
Two months, two and a half months before they got.
And meanwhile, they were fighting everywhere, right?
And the Germans were still there.
So...
Sorry, I didn't mean to bring up anything painful.
Well, yeah.
It took me years before I could eat turnips and whatever, I guess, and even carrots, because you eat those every day, every day, every day.
because the German officers said, you know, the butter, the meat, and what they didn't go to, you know, the NCOs, but not to us.
Plus, you never know, I mean, there were all the concentration camp business, and you never know who's gonna get arrested next.
In a way, I was lucky because I was only five, six, seven years old, and I didn't realize at that time how, you know, and that's one of my regrets.
I never
realized until much, much later how much my dad, you know, having accepted my mother and me through all the stuff that he had to get through.
We owe him a lot.
I think it's
very brave of you to, you've gone through all of that, and then just to enlist.
I think it's very, sorry, that's not a personal comment, but I think somebody who's gone through something like that and then still faces it head on, that's very brave.
Now, to get back to the food problem, no, I'm sorry.
I was so thin that after the liberation, the Red Cross
sent me to Switzerland to go eat, really, for, I don't remember, several, maybe a couple of months.
I was a farmer that accepted, you know, not really refugees, but
I presume the Red Cross paid them something to do that.
And yet, look, I'm 88, so I guess physical constitution was pretty good after all.
What were some differences coming over to America, like even culturally,
Yeah, that was a big change.
But there's several things that just totally amazed me.
And I mentioned four, five, six families.
They knew me because I worked there, but that was it.
The Air Force colonel and his family, they kind of adopted me.
the others, and yet they all spent a lot of time trying to find me a teaching job.
Wow.
That really amazed me.
The
In general, the reception from, again, Peterborough is a small town, and maybe that helps.
But I was, those people are really nice.
And, you know, inviting me for barbecues, for this, for family occasions.
Of course, I wish I just remembered their names, but I always don't.
And the guy that was in another, that offered me the second job, that was in another town.
But I don't think that would have happened in France.
The ham radio group, yes, but outside of that, these were not hams.
My boss was, but...
And another thing that I wasn't paid very much, understandably, but enough to buy a second-hand car.
It was old, but it was
working.
Whoa, that's great.
And the other thing, people don't believe me when I tell them, but the gasoline was 25 cents a gallon in 1964.
So, of course, we were, you know.
So I was able to go around, yeah, my
My work permit didn't allow me to leave New Hampshire, but New Hampshire's pretty good, pretty large.
And the people were very friendly.
Another thing, later on, when I started working for General Telephone, we bought a house, not right away, but, and
So I was an engineer, master's degree.
And the guy next to me was a truck driver.
And I thought, that's amazing.
It could never happen in France.
A, because, I mean, it's a social structure.
You can, you're just a truck driver.
And the guy was very nice, by the way.
But I thought, that's fantastic.
There's a,
it's, on the other hand, so it's not the social status, it's the salary that, right?
We were paid, yeah, obviously made good salary.
So people combined based on their,
financial status rather than social status.
But I kind of like that.
Now that you point that out, I guess that has a lot to do with the government maybe?
Well, the history, I think.
I mean, France, Paris was, when I was there, 2,000 years old, and now it's another 200 years.
There's a whole, yeah, most of Western Europe, England included, there's this social thing.
which is another thing that ham radio helps, because during those meetings, there was no, you didn't talk about, you know, I'm, you know, Dr. So-and-so, which was ham radio.
So that was true in France, too.
But now there were a lot of, and the opportunities later on, it,
Yeah, in fact, of course now it wouldn't work either, but I was going to say, in France, without a PhD, you can't be teaching at the university, period.
Here, that's true now, but because engineering technology was not preparing people for grad school, they say, okay, you don't have a PhD, but you've got 10 years of industrial experience, so for us, that's actually good.
They no longer do that.
In fact, when I...
One year I made the outstanding prof for, you know, the College of Engineering.
Each college has one, and I did it for the College of Engineering.
So big receptions and speeches.
And I was, so the ten of us are sitting together on the podium.
And I hear the lady at that time who was in charge of the faculty, she was reading some letters from my students and compliments and very nice.
But I was, so that's 19, I'm sorry, 2000, yeah.
But
If I applied now, you wouldn't even look at my resume because I don't have a doctorate, right?
So it's kind of ironic, but in France there is no exception.
You can't teach at the university if you don't have a PhD.
Interesting.
So that was a plus.
And even, well, the junior college they wouldn't require, but the technical school in France, no, there you don't need a PhD either.
So, there's definitely more opportunities here than to think.
Things have changed in Europe a lot, but in that time, it was much more structured.
Yeah, that makes sense.
This life here is very comfortable.
Lots of, what's the right word?
Lots of stuff you couldn't do elsewhere, I think.
It's a bit frenetic.
There is something in France and the other Western European country.
You have five weeks of vacation.
Paid.
So you've got a lot more time to spend with your kids.
That I missed.
And you could travel.
I mean, I used to travel with my parents until I was...
21 or something like that, that we would still go together because there's no perfect place.
But I'm certainly grateful to this one, which is why I joined the Coast Guard Auxiliary, which is the volunteer branch of the Coast Guard, and I just completed my 25th year with them.
That was my way of saying thanks, and here, maybe I can help.
Yeah, I got my fourth gold star.
The ribbon is the first five years, then they're each gold star is another five years.
Yeah, that, yeah.
So I still do that.
Of course, I don't go on patrols anymore, boat patrols anymore, and I don't do physical stuff because I don't have the strength, and I have usual age problems.
But I'm still a member, I'm still their communication officer for some strange reason.
I was the HR officer for the division level.
I stepped down from that last year because I was forgetting too many things.
It's embarrassing when you're in HR, you deal with all the newcomers, right?
Then you help, you have to do this and this.
And then three weeks later, the guy would come back and...
Do I know you?
I mean, that's normal at my age.
Yeah, in fact, we're going to have, we call that the flotilla, it's on Lake Conroe, and we're going to have a common maneuver training the end of May, May 30th.
Together with the regular Coast Guard, the fire department, they have several rescue and fire boats.
And the Lake Constable, we do a common maneuver, which is part of training.
We do search and rescue type thing.
Normally it's done on Galveston Bay, but it's...
And we, yeah, we're the volunteer branch.
We don't do law enforcement, but everything else.
Public education, boat inspection, we do public affairs.
radio communications when needed, and essentially whatever the regular Coast Guard would like us to do.
It goes all the way to cooks, I mean chefs that were chefs in their previous life and are retired.
And in fact that started in our division when they
I don't think it was the captain, but one of the officers of the regular ghost girl said, wait a minute, do you have people who know how to cook?
Yeah, we need them.
We don't have enough.
We have boats that cannot go out on shore because the only thing we have are sandwiches.
And so there we have people that go help them at Galveston, but also fewer of them because you now have to go spend a week or two offshore with them.
So we also have people who help them, administratively speaking, because they are so busy these days.
both from a protection of the coast, that's a job, right, but blocking and you name it.
And that's the role that they used to have, which included
boating safety of the public, right?
They say, look, we really have less and less time.
You guys do that.
So that's why we do patrol in Galveston Bay regularly and we have that on Lake Conroe and many of the lakes to reduce the number of accidents and deaths on the water.
So since you've gone all over, moved everywhere, do you have anything else on your bucket list?
Any places you want to visit?
Well, I've been to quite a few places.
That's the thing.
You know, I mentioned the five-week vacation with my parents.
We could go
all over Western Europe.
I did go to Eastern Europe to what was then Czechoslovakia as part of my job that first year for just a couple of weeks.
But Prague is a very nice city.
And my wife is actually from East Germany.
They escaped just before the wall was completely closed.
But of course, now it's recombined, so we went together with her brother, visiting where they were born.
And that was interesting.
In fact, the mayor somehow
I guess her brother just went to the city hall to say, we're here for a visit, and we used to, I guess the mayor got interested and rejoined us and took us around.
It was really nice.
Yeah, I've been to lots of places.
Also,
I was a part-time contractor with USAID, which doesn't exist anymore.
One department of USAID was the Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance.
They go and help people right after, you know, hurricanes, volcanic eruption.
to do help wherever needed.
And of course, one problem, especially the smaller Caribbean islands, is they get wiped out.
And they have no way to call for help.
Well, dependent situation.
So one of the things I did with another ham who was working for them full time,
is we would go down and do a temporary either shortwave radio communication or we had a portable satellite station and set it up so they can talk either to Geneva, the Red Cross, or to Washington for the health organization.
Doctors Without Borders?
No, no, I mean the government.
Well, it's international, not international, multinational power.
The aid show is health organization, oh, Pan American Health Organization.
For example, sometimes they would ask USAID, can you send us some guys?
So, went to Guatemala and do that.
They didn't do much others.
Well, Mexico, yeah, but did sailing to Mexico several times.
Alpanama on the Atlantic side.
And yeah, a lot of Western, essentially most of Western Europe.
I have lots of cousins, distant cousins.
We had one major family, greater family reunion in
Yeah, in November of 2000, first year I was retired, organized by people over there.
And we had about 110 or 114 people from nine different countries, all descended from the same great-great-grandfather.
And we were in that—it took place in the town where those grandfathers had lived.
And, I mean, there was, we had people, yeah, including a family from Hungary.
And at that time, in 2000, there was
free traveling again.
They had to go through all kinds of things.
They drove all the way down to the east of France to join us.
That's where my family was from.
Yeah.
And so we had people from Italy,
Interestingly enough, we, nobody from Spain, yet Catala is definitely, it's from the northern, northeastern part, the place called Catalonia, in fact, which is a province, that in their language, Catalan, Catala means somebody from Catalonia, so we know we have ancestors there, but we couldn't go that far.
So it was strange that we had people from Argentina, we had people from England, Germany, Italy, France of course.
And I visited a lot of these people because
We, that group that organized this reunion, then two years later, well, we go to another country where we're, and by that time I was part of the committee.
So, yeah, I, yeah, traveling I did, a lot.
In Canada, after I was here, one of our daughters lived in Washington State, almost in Canada, on the Pacific Ocean.
So we have a camper van and we, several times, three times we've gone there, took our time going and spent a month there and come back at different routes and in fact, through Canada.
Yeah.
let's see, of course Haiti, Jamaica, and while I was there, so I was working for the International Telecommunication Union, but the United Nations,
I'm sorry, I'm going to blame.
Anyhow, they also, that's the specialized agency, the UN, that deals with disasters.
And when I was in Haiti, usually all the project managers would get together once every two months or so to exchange ideas.
And we had a representative from...
And he said, oh, you're in telecom.
We need help in the Caribbean with us.
I said, okay.
I've got a full-time job here.
I said, Tim, who's your boss?
Geneva.
I said, oh, we're in Geneva, too.
They organized something and I was allowed to, you know, take, I don't remember, four days off a month to go.
So, and I visited the different islands, all the independent ones, not Puerto Rico and, you know, the ones that are still...
territories or whatever, they have their civil defense organized.
But the others need help.
So I would stay several days in this island and another month in that island, which, yeah, I know the Caribbean fairly well.
Wow, what a life.
You've lived so much.
You've seen so much.
Yeah, I have been...
Ever since the war stopped, I've been very lucky.
Interesting.
I know you mentioned how you were writing some chapters to a book, but I think you should write your own book about places you've been to.
I'd for sure read that.
Yeah.
I don't have any more questions.
Did you have anything that you wanted to talk about that I didn't get to?
Yeah, a couple of things.
One thing when I did decide to come here is when I thought, oh good, I'm gonna
stop all the political problems.
You work for the UN and in a foreign country, you've got to deal with a lot of different things.
First, you've got colleagues that are from five different countries.
We all have our own views of things, and those are the five experts.
and then you've got our counterparts and of course they the whole country right and there are things that are perfectly okay the u.s or but not at all okay they say and and you don't have time to learn all you learn the hard way so it
I mean, again, I'm not regretting any of that.
But it's different.
It's different.
Haiti, in particular, is a very poor country.
And they have a former French colony and then the history of slavery.
And there are things that you just don't do.
So if you ask something from somebody in a way that can be answered by yes or no, they can't say no.
Oh.
You can't say no to a superior, right?
And especially a foreigner, a blanc, yeah, white guy.
So they say yes.
And then you say, you've finished that.
I attested it's not working.
I said, no, I don't know how to do that.
But I ask you if you've done it.
Yes.
And I'm like, what's going on?
So I went to see my colleague, my counterpart, who was an engineer, and he said, well, no, it's not an acceptable answer in this.
Oh, geez.
So you've got to make sure you ask.
In fact, one time, we were looking for a place for a microwave repeater.
We were in countryside, jeep fording rivers, and...
And on the way back, I got totally lost.
There was a lady sitting in front of a hut, literally.
And I asked her, you know, is this the way to Port-au-Prince?
Guess what she answered?
Yes, right?
So I go there and we drive for hours, maybe not, but for a long time.
I said, I don't reckon any of this.
Turn around.
He said, one of the, it wasn't my counterpart, but one of the Asian colleagues, he was in training, he was an installer, said, do you mind if I ask the questions?
He said, please.
So he stated in Creole, not in French, but I understood.
He said, which is the way for Port-au-Prince?
And then, that way, I thought.
Well, yeah, I should have...
Ideally, you have an advance notice, you've got a month to read about, but that's not the way things happen.
I had one week and a half to make a decision whether I would go to Haiti or not.
Yeah, that was interesting.
Yeah, cultural differences, yeah.
See, I wouldn't even think about that.
I would have that problem as well.
Yeah, it's their history, and they still suffer from it.
And actually, the other problem is
even within a telephone company, the position that you occupy or you occupy is
really a political assignment.
Okay.
So, at least at the higher level.
So you have situation where a supervisor, and I pointed out, said, did you see what he did?
Yeah.
That's dangerous.
Yes, but I don't want to give him a hard time.
Because two months from now, maybe the doc might put him as my boss's boss.
So can I tell him?
Yes, please do.
So even in those instances, you still have to play politics?
Yeah, well, so yeah, you're right, I diverged.
So I thought, I'm through with all this political... No.
That was a surprise.
Although I've been very lucky with all my department heads.
Some interesting times.
Yeah.
Again, if I had known that I wouldn't have any vacation, I probably would have said no, because I had an offer from industry in San Diego, and of course, but that's the way it is.
I wouldn't have a chance to have this relationship with the students, so.
Thank you for meeting me and telling me your story, a bit of your story.
I'm glad if it could be useful.
Absolutely, it is.
Absolutely.
We have roughly 2,000 interviews from the 60s all the way up to the early 2000s from previous history.
One of them was the director of our library, Cushing.
And the other one, Terry Anderson, he's still here.
He's a history professor.
I don't know if you know him.
I know the school's huge, but he's still here.
And so once I got hired and I basically got all of his work that he had, I was like, it's so nice to meet you.
And I'm the one handling all of your interviews that you've given me.
He's like, oh, no, those things, put them back in the closet.
Put them back in the closet.
Yeah.
Oh, good.
Thank you so much.
You're very welcome.
Glad to help.
Yes.
I will be in touch.
I will make sure you get copies of everything.
Now, your wife sounds like someone I should talk to, too.
She is quite a lady.
She's kept me for 57 years.
That by itself, she's the nurse, was a nurse.
after we came back from Haiti.
She had been interested in medical stuff for a long time and did some of it over because the places were, you know, Haiti and...
to a lesser extent Jamaica, where if you have to do something rapidly, there's no ambulance coming, right?
So she read lots of books and things, and decided that she wanted to—we came back in, well, 1984.
She couldn't really become a doctor, but she decided, I'm going to be a nurse.
and I was here on campus so practically all the time.
She managed with the four girls who were, well, twins were in senior year, and then Yvonne was
two years behind.
And then the little one, we adopted a baby in Haiti.
So, schoolgirls, and she was studying for nursing, taking classes in the evening, you know, as we say in French, hats off.
It's an amazing lady.
And
I mean, she had a rough youth too.
The war was over, but I mean, East Germany was under, you know, communist thing.
Yeah, her dad had a small factory and he had to escape.
and her mother, her brother, and her escaped two years later, right before they completely closed the wall.
And so they had to start their life all over in West Germany.
Yeah, they had a rough time too.
If she does want to talk.
I would love to hear her story as well.
I will ask.
She probably not.
She, for several reasons, doesn't like to talk about... That's understandable.
But she's right now helping our...